- [Instructor] Today, we're going to learn
about event handling in JavaScript.
Event handling allows us to listen for and respond
to user actions like clicks, drags and more.
This is a key part of making our webpage interactive.
In this lesson, we'll add event listeners
to our plant elements to handle the drag event.
we'll update our script.js file to listen for when the user
clicks on a plant element and starts dragging it.
Before we continue on, let's talk about event listeners.
Event listeners are functions
that wait for specific events to occur,
and then execute a predefined code
in response to those events.
Let's break down some key components of event listeners.
First, there's event types.
Events in JavaScript can be triggered by user interactions
like clicks or key presses,
or even changes in the document, like resizing.
Next, there's targets.
Every event is associated
with a particular element in the DOM.
We call this the event target.
For example, if you click on a button,
the button is the event target for the click event.
Next is the event handler function.
It contains code that should be executed
when that particular event occurs.
Another crucial step in event handling
is adding the event listener.
And this process really is about attaching
an event listener to a particular element.
In our code, we'll add an event listener
for the pointer down event.
This event is triggered when the user presses
a pointer button like a mouse click on the element.
Notice, the onpointerdown property
is set to our pointerDrag function.
This is notated by the equal sign in between the two.
We haven't created our pointerDrag function yet,
but we'll do that next.
What pointerDrag will do will handle the initial actions
when the user starts dragging the element.
So, let's go ahead and add it now.
Our pointerDrag function is ready to go.
The pointerDrag function
takes an event object (e) as its parameter.
The e.preventDefault method
prevents any default actions that might occur
when the event is triggered.
The console.log statement logs the event object
to the console, which is useful for debugging.
Let's break this function down even further.
First, let's talk about the parameter (e).
This parameter represents the event object.
It contains information about the event
that triggered the function.
In this case, the event is a pointer or mouse press.
You're probably wondering, what's an object?
Objects allow you to store multiple values
in a single variable.
Each are identified by a unique key
and come in a collection of key value pairs.
Objects are used to model and represent
real world entities and their properties,
making it easier to manage and manipulate related data.
Another key point about objects,
especially as they relate to events,
is that objects come with predefined functions,
also maybe known as methods.
Objects also come with methods or functions.
And functions when they relate to objects
have a specific mission and goal.
For example, we've been working
with document.getElementById.
getElementByIdwhich is part of the document object
looks in the DOM for an element of a particular ID,
in the case of our plants.
That brings us to the e.preventDefault line.
This line prevents the default behavior of the event.
For instance, when you click and drag an image,
the browser might try to drag the image as a default action.
We don't want that to happen,
so we use this line to stop it.
Next, we log the event.
This logs the event object to the console.
The console is a tool built in the browsers
that allows developers to see information
about their code as it runs.
You might have seen a little bit of this in the CSS chapter.
By logging e, we can see details about the pointer event,
which is useful for debugging and understanding
what's happening when the function is triggered.
We'll see this in action shortly.
Next, we're using the pos3 and the pos4 variables
that we defined earlier.
Remember, pos3 and the pos4
store the current cursor position on the X and Y axis.
Summing up what these lines do,
they store the initial position of the mouse cursor.
So, e.clientX gives a horizontal coordinate
on the X axis of the mouse pointer.
And e.clientY gives a vertical coordinate or on the Y axis.
This all happens when the event occurs.
We save them in our variables
and this helps us calculate how far the cursor moves.
Finally, in these last two lines,
we're setting up event listeners for dragging.
The first one,
onpointermove means that while the pointer is moving,
the element drag function will be called continuously.
This function will handle updating
the position of the elements as you drag it.
The way that document.onpointerup works
is that when you release the pointer button,
the stopElementDrag function will be called.
And this function will stop the dragging process.
We haven't written these functions yet,
so let's go ahead and do that.
Let's break down what these two functions,
elementDrag and stopElementDrag do.
elementDrag is responsible for updating the position
of the terrariumElement as a user drags it.
First, it calculates the new cursor position.
The math here that you're seeing
represents how much the mouse has moved
since the last mouse move event.
And then in the next two lines,
we update the stored cursor position.
The next two lines are responsible for moving the element.
And here, we're actually manipulating the DOM through CSS.
terrariumElement.style.top sets the top position
of the element by adjusting its current top position
by the amount the mouse has moved vertically.
terrariumElement.style.left does the same thing
except on the left position.
So it adjusts its current left position
by the amount the mouse has moved horizontally.
And all this really here is doing
is moving the element to follow the mouse movement.
So, every time you drag a plant,
it follows your mouse cursor.
Let's talk about stopElementDrag.
This function is responsible for stopping
the drag operation when the user releases the mouse button.
onpointerup = null removes the event listener
for the pointer up event.
And what this really means
is that the stopElementDrag function
will no longer be called when the mouse button is released.
Same thing for onpointermove.
It removes the event listener for the pointermove event
so that the elementDrag function will no longer be called
when the mouse moves.
All this really means here is that the element
will stay in its new position,
and no further updates to its position will be made
until a new drag operation is initiated.
And that's it for this lesson.
If we go ahead and try and run our terrarium,
what we'll find is that things don't work quite yet,
and that's okay.
We have a couple more steps here
before we make this terrarium come to life.
In this lesson, we learned about event handling
and added event listeners to our plant elements.
This allows us to respond to user actions
like clicks and drags.
We spent a lot of time here
and that's because understanding event handling is crucial
for creating interactive webpage.
In the next lesson, we'll talk a little bit more
about things we need to add
to make our terrarium come to life.
And that'll be closures.
See you soon.