- [Instructor] Welcome back.
Today we're going to learn about closures in JavaScript.
Closures are a powerful feature that allow an inner function
to access variables from its outer function.
This is especially useful for managing state
and keeping track of data over time.
Let's learn a little bit more about closures.
A closure is a function that remembers the variables
from the place where it was created,
even when the function is executed in a different context.
Think of it like a backpack.
When the function is created,
it packs some variables in its backpack.
No matter where the function goes,
it carries those variables with it.
Let's talk about why we need closures.
I mentioned before that closures allow us
to keep track of data over time,
and this is really key in situations where we're working
with asynchronous operations,
which we'll learn about a little later,
or when dealing with event listeners.
In our draggable terrarium, we need to keep track
of the position of the mouse
and the element while it's being dragged.
So what we'll need to do is keep track of some state
between the start and end of this operation,
and this is where our closure will be particularly useful.
In our last lesson, we talked about event handling
and how specific functions carry out
specific event handling tasks for us.
As we can see in our code, quite a few of our functions here
need to know the mouse position.
However, dragElement is a function
that stores our cursor position variables.
How can we reconfigure our code
so that all functions have access
to these four position variables?
This is where closures come in.
We said that closures consist of outer and inner functions.
So in this case, since dragElement
is storing these four variables,
we'll want to make dragElement the outer function.
So let's get coding.
First thing I'm going to do is take my cursor over here
and confirm that the curly braces
for my dragElement function are where I expect them to be.
I can rely on Visual Studio Code to do this.
And I can see here that when I put my cursor
next to my closing curly brace,
my opening curly brace is highlighted.
Since I verified my closing curly brace,
I'll go ahead and delete that curly brace.
Then I'll scroll all the way to the bottom
and add my closing curly brace at the bottom of my code.
You probably notice that when I deleted that curly brace,
I had a bunch of squiggly lines all over my code.
That's just letting me know I'm missing a line of code.
Visual Studio Code is really great at letting us know
when our syntax is off.
Okay, so I've added my curly brace,
and now all of my inner functions
are inside of the dragElement outer function.
We've successfully created closure.
Let's go back to that backpack analogy.
You put your items, which we can consider as variables
in your backpack, which is our closure.
So during our trip, no matter where you are,
you can take your items out of your backpack
when it's needed.
And in this case, the functions inside dragElement
carry the position variables with them
and use them as needed during the dragging process.
So in the case of a function like elementDrag,
which is called repeatedly adjusting the element's position,
it uses the same pos1, 2, 3, and 4 variables
to calculate the new position.
This is the case for pointerDrag as well as stopElementDrag.
One last step I want to take here
is move the two dragElement function calls
on line six and seven outside of my closure.
I hope you understand now why these two lines of code
didn't work in our prior lesson.
Without closures, the inner functions
would lose track of the position variables,
and the drag and drop functionality wouldn't work.
Closures allow these inner functions to maintain access
to the necessary variables,
ensuring the elements can be correctly dragged and dropped.
So let's go ahead and give our terrarium a spin.
We can see in our code here that only plant1 and plant2
are draggable at this time.
And don't worry, we'll fix this up soon
so that the other plants also have the same functionality.
For now, let's test plants one and two,
and those plants are at the top left of our page.
And we can see here that we were easily able
to drag our two plants into our terrarium.
We can also see that we can't drag
these other plants quite yet, but we'll get there shortly.
Congratulations, we've made our terrarium interactive,
thanks to closures.
In the next lesson, we'll put it all together.
See you there.