- [Instructor] Today, I have a special topic for you.
Today, we're going to learn about manipulating the DOM
using JavaScript.
The DOM or Document Object Model represents the structure
of our webpage as a tree of objects.
JavaScript allows us to interact with the DOM,
making our webpages dynamic and interactive.
In this lesson, we'll use JavaScript
to select our plant elements by their Id,
so we can make them draggable.
Recall in our HTML chapter that we gave
all of our elements, these Id attributes.
Those are going to come into play now.
So let's get into it.
Here in our script.js file,
we'll be using the document.getElementbyId
method to select our plant elements.
Let's add our line of code and talk about it.
What document.getElementbId does
is it looks for an element
with a matching Id in the parentheses.
This method returns the HTML element
with the specified Id.
Let's repeat this process for plant two.
What I've done here is copied line five, pasted it below
and updated the plant one string to plant two.
So now, here in this code, we'll be seeking elements
with an Id of plant one and an Id of plant two.
Let's take a step back
and talk a little bit more about functions and what they do.
We talked about how functions can take
in a particular thing called a parameter.
And in our case is taking in a terrarium element.
Here, we're actually using it.
So here, on line five and six,
we're passing the HTML elements with the Id
of plant one or plant two into drag element.
So now, these elements will be these
particular terrarium elements here.
In the function definition,
the terrarium element is called a parameter.
And here in the function when we're using it,
also known as calling it, we put the actual value
of the parameter.
And at this point it's called an argument
inside the parentheses.
And so, to work with a function
and to actually run the code that's inside of it,
in between the curly braces, we write down its name,
we add a pair of parentheses,
and if there's a parameter that needs to be passed in,
we put it in between the parentheses.
So let's wrap it up.
We learned about manipulating the DOM using JavaScript.
We use the document.getElementbyId method
to select our plant elements by their Id
and called the drag element function to make them draggable.
Understanding how to manipulate the DOM is essential
for creating dynamic and interactive webpages.
It's a lot of fun.
In the next lesson, we'll learn about event handling
and how to respond to user actions.
Stay tuned.