- [Narrator] Welcome back.
We just went through a really amazing series on CSS
and really gave our terrarium life.
In this final section, we're going to walk through JavaScript.
It's the programming language
that gives our elements interactivity, so let's get started.
First, we're going to learn about variables.
Variables are fundamental in any programming language,
including JavaScript.
They're containers that hold data values,
which can be numbers, text, or even more complex data.
Before we continue on,
let's check out our container, our terrarium.
This is the state of our terrarium
after we finished up adding our CSS.
We have our plants on either side of our jar.
We have our jar in the middle with that nice little glow
and shine in the bottom left,
and we can see that everything is adequately positioned,
and we also know that we can't drag
and drop these plants in here just yet.
That's what JavaScript's for.
Let's get back to variables.
Think of a variable as a box that you can store things in.
You can put a value in the box.
You can take it out or change it to whatever you need to.
In JavaScript, we're can use a Let, Const
or Var keywords to declare a variable.
Choosing between Let, Var or Const
is like choosing between reusable
or single use containers.
We recommend Let, for most cases.
Let's talk about Const.
If you have a value that should always stay the same,
use Const.
It's like a locked box.
Let's move on to our terrarium.
For our draggable terrarium, we'll need to keep track
of the position of our elements as they are being dragged.
We'll use variables to store those positions.
Let's open up the script.js file,
Here, I've opened the script.js file.
We can see that it's empty.
That's where we come in.
Before we get started,
I just want to hop into my index.html file
and make sure my script.js file is referenced.
I'll add it here on line nine, great.
Let me give myself some more space.
Close my index.html file, and we are ready to go.
First things first, let's go ahead and add some variables.
At the top of the file,
we'll declare four variables using the Let keyword
and these variables will store the initial
and current positions of the mouse cursor.
Here's what each variable represents.
pos1 and pos2 will store the change
in cursor position on the X and Y axis.
pos3 and pos4 will store the current cursor
position on the X and Y axis.
By setting these variables to zero initially,
we ensure that they have a defined value
before we start using them
to track positions, and that's it.
In this lesson, we introduced variables, which are essential
for storing and manipulating data in JavaScript.
We declared four variables
that will help us track the position
of our elements while they are being dragged.
Understanding variables is crucial
because they allow us to store
and work with data dynamically.
In the next lesson, we'll learn about functions
and how they can perform tasks for us in JavaScript.
See you then.