- Today we're stepping into the world of JavaScript.
- That's right, Jasmine.
If we think of our website as a house,
JavaScript is what turns it from a static structure
into a home with lights, doors that open, and much more.
- [Jasmine] So if HTML is the structure of our house
and CSS is the design,
JavaScript is the electricity that powers everything inside.
- Exactly.
JavaScript lets us interact with the elements on the page.
You can think of it as installing smart home devices
that react to your actions.
- With just a few lines of code,
you can make your website respond to user actions.
- It's like turning on a light with a switch.
JavaScript can show or hide information on a webpage,
change colors,
or even create new content dynamically.
- It's what makes the web feel alive.
Without JavaScript,
our house would be dark and unresponsive,
but with it, we can make it welcoming and interactive.
- And the best part?
You can start small
and gradually add more features as you learn.
It's like furnishing your house one room at a time.
- To sum up, JavaScript adds functionality to our websites.
It's an essential skill for web developers,
and we're excited to dive deeper into it with you.