- [Instructor] So let's get back to our code
and add the functionality we need to make
the rest of our plants draggable.
We're back in our script.js file.
As we know, we've already added draggable functionality
to plant one and plant two with the drag element function.
All we need to do at this point is do the same thing
for the 12 other plants, and at this point,
copy and paste is our best friend.
So let's get to it.
I'm going to take a different approach here
and copy these two lines of code
and paste them,
because we have a lot of plants to add here.
So, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14.
We should have 14 lines of code here.
Just counting my lines here.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14.
Perfect.
And now I just need to renumber my plants.
If you're curious at this point,
you could try and experiment with this code,
but the functionality should remain the same.
Only plant one and plant two will be draggable.
And there we are.
All of our plants should be draggable at this point
because they've all been added as arguments
for the drag element function.
So they all should respond to my dragging behavior.
Let's give it a try.
After a refresh, we're giving our terrarium a spin.
I'm taking a moment here to be a little creative
with my terrarium,
make it look nice and pretty.
Notice that I can nest my plants on top or below each other.
That's thanks to CSS.
That looks pretty nice.
Let's go ahead and add maybe something
a little bit tall here.
Maybe not that one.
Let's go ahead and add this one at the end here.
Beautiful. I'm really happy with my little terrarium here.
Thanks to HTML CSS and JavaScript
we're able to make a beautiful terrarium
that's super interactive.
Now that we've tested it out,
made sure everything works properly,
we have successfully created our terrarium.
Thank you for following along with this series.
I hope this was a super fun project for you.
There's so much more to learn about JavaScript,
so keep practicing
and exploring more to enhance your web development skills,
and we'll be doing just that in our next chapter.
Happy coding.