- [Instructor] Today, we're going to talk
about functions in JavaScript.
Functions are one of the most important concepts
in programming.
They allow us to group a set of instructions
into a single unit that can be executed whenever we need it.
Think of a function as a blueprint
for a home improvement project.
The blueprint contains all the instructions
and measurements you need to follow
to complete the project.
Instead of figuring out the steps and measurements
every time you want to do a similar project,
you just refer to the blueprint.
Similarly, instead of writing the same code multiple times,
you write a function and call it whenever you need
to perform a similar task in your program.
Here in our script.js file,
we're going to create a new function called dragElement.
This function will take an HTML element as an argument,
which is defined as terrariumElement here.
This function that I just created here
will take an HTML element as an argument
and make it draggable.
The "function" keyword
is used to declare a function in JavaScript.
The name of our function is dragElement,
and it takes one parameter called terrariumElement.
This parameter represents the HTML element
that we want to make draggable.
Inside the function,
we're going to copy the code that we have on line 1,
and paste it into the body of this function
between the curly braces.
We've moved our position variables inside of the function
to ensure that they are scoped correctly
within the function.
This is going to be important
for tracking the position of the element
during the drag operation.
In this case, the element
that we're going to be dragging are the plants.
So essentially, the terrariumElement parameter here
will be the particular plant
that we will be clicking on and dragging.
And that's it for functions,
which allow us to group a set of instructions
into a single unit
that can be executed whenever we need it.
We created a function called dragElement
that will eventually handle
the dragging of our terrariumElements.
Understanding functions is crucial
because they help us organize our code
and make it more reusable.
In the next lesson,
we'll learn about the document object model,
also known as a DOM.
We'll learn about what it is,
and how to manipulate it using JavaScript.
See you soon.